Inventory of the Katherine Ream Sobeck Papers, 1942-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
Katherine Ream Sobeck Papers, 1942-2010
2010C33
Sobeck, Katherine Ream
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Materials in this collection were acquired by Katherine Ream Sobeck. The collection is comprised of memoirs, correspondence, internee lists, newsletters, other printed matter, and photographs related to the experiences of American civilians interned by the Japanese during their occupation of the Philippines in World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Francis Willard Brush papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Ann Miller Depew papers, Hoover Institution Archives
James J. Halsema papers, Hoover Institution Archives
George C. Mora papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Renee Ream collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Katherine Ream Sobeck was born December 7, 1929, in Manila, Philippines. She was living in Baguio, Philippines with her family at the time the Japanese invaded the islands during World War II. Members of Katherine Ream Sobeck's family were civilian internees throughout the Japanese occupation of the Philippines, at first at Camp John Hay and Camp Holmes in Baguio City, and subsequently at the Bilibid Prison in Manila. The Ream family moved to California in May 1945. Katherine married Frederick J. on Sobeck September 1, 1950, in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and divorced in September 1977. She now resides in Maryland.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Katherine Ream Sobeck collection is comprised of memoirs, correspondence, internee lists, newsletters, other printed matter, and photographs related to the experiences of American civilians interned by the Japanese during their occupation of the Philippines in World War II. Content is comprised of transcripts, photocopies and copies of original materials.
Over time Katherine Ream Sobeck came into the possession of unpublished copies of internee diaries and memoirs, newspaper clippings, camp related papers, and photographs documenting the experiences of American internees in Japanese-occupied Philippines, specifically at the Baguio and Bilibid internment camps. In 2010 Katherine Ream Sobeck donated these materials to the Hoover Institution Archives.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Americans--Philippines; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines--Concentration camps; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945
Collection Contents
- Memoirs and Correspondence, 1942-2004
  All content photocopies and transcriptions of originals.
  - Camp John Hay memoirs, undated (Folder 1: 1)
    Written accounts by various authors who were children during internment. Includes letters by Ruth Ream, list of internees, illustrations and photographs. (3 copies)
  - Katherine Ream Sobeck correspondence, 2003-2004 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Nora Ream Kuttner correspondence, 1990; 1996-1997 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Internee memoirs, 1942-2000, undated (Folder 1: 4)
    Memoirs from internees Woodrow and Sara Bartges, Patricia Briggs Dabbs, Carl B. Eschbach, Sidney Frankel, Betty Halsema Foley, Jim Halsema, Sylvan Katz, John F. Ream, Jim Thompson and unknown authors.
  - Ream family memoirs, undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Rokuro Tomibe (former Commandant, Camp Holmes) correspondence and documents, 1975-1983, undated (Folder 1: 6)
    Newspaper clippings related to 1977 internee reunion, an early translated draft of war time memoir The Secret Story of the War's End by Rokuro Tomibe and published version.
- Internment Camp Materials, 1942-1948; 1988; (bulk 1942-1948)
  All content photocopies or copies of originals.
  - Camp documents, 1944 (Folder 1: 7)
    Inventory of Red Cross packages, high school exam papers, bulletin board notices and daily newsletter.
  - Camp drawings and maps, undated (Folder 1: 8)
  - Internee rosters, 1942-1948, undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Photographs, 1942-1945; 1988, undated (Folder 1: 10)
- Miscellaneous Materials, 1945-2010
  - Baguio Internee News, 2007-2010 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Internee reunions, 1976-2010 (Folder 1: 12)
    Documents, pamphlets and photographs associated with internee reunions.
  - Miscellaneous, 1945-1995, undated (Folder 1: 13)
    American POW articles, maps, journal article, war claim document, Douglas MacArthur communications and research paper by Romilda Wilder.
  - Newspaper and magazine articles, 1945-1963; 1977-2007, undated (Folder 1: 14)
    Newspaper and magazine articles written by and about internees..